<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dyetary of ghostly helthe</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1520</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6833</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845217</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10104</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10104)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 34:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dyetary of ghostly helthe</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Impry[n]ted by me wynkyn de worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The yere of our lorde. M.CCCCC. [and] xx. Of Noue[m]bre the .xx. daye.] [1520]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustrations on title leaf, recto and verso.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁶ b⁴ c⁶.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10104:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10104:1"/>
            <p>¶ The Dyetary of ghoſtly helthe.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a young nun or female figure in a church or convent, kneeling at a lectern with a book; a halo fans out from her head and from her heart three beams which pass through a cloud to three triple-crowned female figures, one holding an orb and one giving a blessing; in the top corners, facing each other, are an angel and a devil or demon</figDesc>
                  <p>¶ Contemplacio \\ ſacratiſſime \\ dei. Genitricis \\ ſemper<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> \\ virgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s \\ marte \\</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10104:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of an older nun seated, writing in a book, with an angel on her shoulder and a smaller male figure or monk and female figure or nun kneeling beside her; beside her stands a pilgrim's staff with a cockle hat and bag or satchel hanging from it, and a crown and shield with a blazon or coat of arms of a lion rampant; above are a bearded and crowned male figure or god cradling the half-naked male figure of the crucified Jesus Christ, while a dove, bird, or the holy spirit descends toward the writing nun; also an angel holding a scroll above a male child or Christ with a halo, near a praying female figure or Virgin Mary in a stable</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:10104:2"/>
            <head>¶ The prologue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the begynny<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of this newe yere / my good ſyſters whan I conſyder and ſe many frendes gyue tokens of cuſtome one to another / whiche cuſtome / ſome vſe it for good lucke of a newe yere / ſome to ꝓcure carnal loue / ſome to get a greater be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefyte therby / ſome to gette worldely fauour or maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce in yll / ſome to pleaſe &amp; flatter them that ben yll / (whiche cauſes ben not commendable) ſome to procure loue and to contynue frendſhyp and peas in the comune lyfe / bytwene neyghbour &amp; neyghbour / whiche is ryght good and conuenyent to do. And ſome with ryght godly intent to purchace ghoſtly loue. For one ghoſtly frende to remembre another the more hartely in prayers / whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I thynke ryght comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable. And after this intent (as I ſuppoſe) dyuers of you haue gyuen tokens vnto me. Wherfore hauynge nothynge redy to gyue vnto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / I purpoſe in my mynde to prepare one token for you all / to profyte eche of you. This token thynke it tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I haue not of my ſelfe / but of god / as I haue herde &amp; redde of holy doctours / and by coniecture of the waye to good lyuynge / and nothynge by experyence of my ſelfe. It is full vnſemynge to me for to ſhewe or wryte vnto you of the waye to vertue / whiche am not yet all out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of wyckednes. Yet a gryndyngſton maketh a knyfe bryght &amp; ſharpe / thoughe it be neuer the ſharper it ſelfe. So I maye moeue you to make you ſharpe &amp; quycke to ghoſtly thynges &amp; to clereneſſe of good lyuynge / though I my ſelfe be ryght ſlowe and dull vnto the ſame. To teche goodneſſe is a thynge that may not be vndone / of them that haue cure &amp; rewle of other perſones / though
<pb facs="tcp:10104:3"/> they do but lytell good themſelfe. Cryſt ſayd of the pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſyes rulers of the people. Do as they ſaye / but not as they do. Not withſtandynge our lorde hathe gyuen me a deſyre to do well. I beſeche hym I maye haue grace to perfourme my deſyre to his pleaſure / honoure &amp; laude. Therfore though my ſymple lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge can ſtyrre you but lytell. I truſt that my good wyll and deſyre that I haue to your ghoſtly profyte ſhall mcyte you bothe to encreace the more in vertu / and alſo to helpe me with your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto the ſame. Alytell Dyetary for your dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I purpoſe for to wryte / deuydy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it into. xxiiij conſyderacyons / as the daye is deuyded into. xxxiiij. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / whiche though it be rudely wryten / it maye profyte you moche / yf ye wyll dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly put it i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> execucyon of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge / and elles it profytech lytell / but rather hurteth. For cryſt ſayth a ſermaunte that knoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of his mayſter and wyll not do therafter ſhalbe bette with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great ſtrokes. And who ſoeuer ſtudyeth for the wyll of god &amp; forgete it not / but dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly put it to workynge / he ſhalbe bleſſed of god / and haue euerlaſtynge Ioye for ſo doynge / yf he perceyuer therin.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="breviary">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10104:3"/>
               <head>¶ To remembre that we ben pylgrymes and to what place we ben towarde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is neceſſary fyrſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder / that we be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here in this lyfe as pylgrymes / hauynge no longe reſtynge place / but alwayes beynge forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des other to heuen were we ſhall haue eternall reſte / orels we ben in the wronge way / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhall lede vs to euerlaſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſorowe. Lerne to knowe that one waye fro that other. And than euery daye wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhall go to do ony thynge / aſke this queſtyon of youre ſelfe / ſayenge in your mynde to your ſelfe. Whyder arte thou goynge / conſyderynge wyſely / whyder ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye of vertue or wyckednes / folowynge cryſte or the deuyll / in the waye to heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or to hell. And ſaye theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes. Vias tuas domine demonſtra michi: et ſe mitas edoce me. Dirige me in veritate tua et doce me: <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abqui"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>qui</ex>
                  </expan>a tues deus ſaluator meꝰ: &amp; te ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nui tota die. Set god for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marke that ye wyll go vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to / take his commaundementes for youre waye &amp; ronne ſtedfaſtly therin. Haue good hope in his goodnes / vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly dyſtruſtynge the dyſceyuable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacyons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / thrugh the whiche many ſoules be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyſceyued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The precyouſneſſe of tyme and the ſhortneſſe of the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ecundarely it is to conſyder the precyouſnes of tyme / whiche is gyuen vs to do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in / for our lyfe paſt and to labour for Ioye in the lyfe to come. And how that god ſhall requyre
<pb facs="tcp:10104:4"/> of euery perſone how he hath expended the tyme gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto hym. And thynke that euery tyme not ſpent to his honour is loſte / and ſhalbe ſtraytly punyſſhed. Behelde how ſhort our tyme is / and how vncertayne / beynge no thynge ſurer but onely this tyme preſent / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is but now / hauynge alwaye dethe ſuſpecte / that cometh vpon vs ſodeynly many dyuers wayes. And make alwaye a ſure rekenynge for the tyme paſt. Sayenge this prayer day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. O bone Iheſu: ſint cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te in obliuione me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a tempora preterita valde male conſumpta. Et concede: vt hoctemporis mei reſidium: ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi ſit honorificum: michi fructuoſum et proxi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo edificatorium. Qui viuis et regnas cum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deo. &amp;c. That is to ſay in Englyſſhe. O good lorde Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu let all my tymes paſt be forgoten before the / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue conſumed very yll. And graunt that this reſydew of my tyme may be vſed in honour &amp; worſhyp vnto the / fruyte full vnto my ſelfe / and edyfyenge to my neyghbour / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che lyueſt with god the fader in vnyte of the holy ghoſt worlde without ende. Amen. And at euery tyme that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clocke dothe ſtryke / conſyder that your lyfe is ſhorted by an houre / ſayenge thus to our lady / for to ſocour you at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of dethe. Maria plena gratie: mater miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordie: tu nos ab hoſte protige: &amp; in hora mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis ſuſcipe. Mary moder full of grace / moder alſo of mercy / defende vs from our enemy / and at the houre of dethe / take vs to thy proteccyon. And ſo I truſte there ſhall come great grace therof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How god is preſent to vs and his angell.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:10104:4"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emembre alwaye that what ſoeuer ye do / our lorde god is alwaye preſent / ſeynge and conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge euery thought / worde / and dede / and ſtraytly ſhall call vs to a acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſary to obſerue good maner and reuerent behauyoure / bothe inwarde in mynde / and outwarde in body / aſwell in chambre or cell as in other ſecrete places / as in preſence of great aſtates / hauynge alwaye honour and reuerence to god / and to our good angell / ferynge &amp; beynge aſhamed to do that thynge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of god / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſholde be aſhamed of in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of men. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone / ſaye ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this verſe. Qui cognoſcis ocul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta cordis: parce peccatis noſtris. Lorde that know eſt the pryuytes of harte / we beſeche the ſpare vs / that we be not dampned for our ſynnes / and great offences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Not onely the body / but alſo the mynde muſte be ſparred vs from the occaſyons of yll.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hynke though ye ſholde be cloſed vp within. iiij. walles. It is not ynough to haue your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes ſparred frome the occaſyons of yll / wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde is wandrynge abrode in carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure / muſynge vpon worldly vanytes / beſyed with wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes and maters of other perſones / and carynge moche for youre frendes and kynneſfolkes / occupyed ſomtyme with vnlawfull and vnclenly thoughtes and deſyres. Therfore ye muſte cloſe vp alſo your mynde and affeccy on fro all ſuche thynges. And that muſt be by often and contynuall remembraunce of god / as nere as ye maye. Cloſe vp and hyde youre loue and mynde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe and large woundes of our lorde Iheſu cryſte by deuoute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce
<pb facs="tcp:10104:5"/> of his pytefull paſſyon / alwaye abydynge there / for there our enemyes dare not medle / but why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ye wyll or not / they wyll entre with you into the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teryall cloyſter / youre enemy the fleſſhe muſt nedes in / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll wyll not be behynde. And as I ſuppoſe / ye ſhall haue of hym more force and ſtronger batayle there than euer ye had before. And that we thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke now ryght lytell and eaſy / ſhall than perchaunce be full harde and greuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us to ouercome. Therfore prepare youre ſelfe manly. Stande faſt in fayth / and remembre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rewarde of your vyctory / truſtynge in god onely for ſtrength.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the worlde bryngeth in trouble vnto rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gous perſones.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He worlde truſſeth his gere &amp; hydeth them in a corner of a mannes ſoule / vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme that he is entred into relygyon. And than the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll bryngeth them to lyght. So that thoſe vanytes / ſynnes / and inquyet beſyneſſe / that ye haue ſene / herde / and ben in / ſhall than come to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce / whiche now ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothynge troubled with / as hyden within you. Than alſo the worlde ſhall ſende vnto you by crafte of the deuyll / tydynges and tale berers whiche ſhall lette you of great profyte / yf ye be not ware. Sparre them out therfore and auoyde them from you / and neuer be gladde to here worldly rumours / ne vayne talkynge. Let not the deuyll hyde vp ſuche thynges in youre ſoules that afterwarde maye put you to trouble. Be neuer gladde to talke and here of other perſones yll demenour / of theyr beaute / theyr countenaunce / theyr apparell / and ſpecyally of detraccyon or backbytynge of
<pb facs="tcp:10104:5"/> ony maner of perſones / but rather flee theyr company / or moeue them to ſaye well / and to ſpeke that is honeſte and conuenyent for to here / ſayenge thus before ye ſhall ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ony worldely perſones. Domine libera ani mam meam a labiis iniquis &amp; lingua doloſa. Good lorde I beſeche the delyuer my ſoule from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of wycked men &amp; from a dyſceyuable tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To order well euery tyme auoydynge ydelneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Han after the counſeyll of ſome good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and order euery tyme of the day to ſome profyte bodely or ghoſtly. So that ydleneſſe before all thynges maye be vtterly excluded. For ydleneſſe is the moder of all yll / ſtepdame to vertue / forger of vnclennes / the way to vnſtableneſſe nuryſſher of vyces / increacer of ſlouthfulneſſe / kynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of malyce and inuye. It ſoweth yll thoughtes. It ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreth yll deſyres / and bryngeth forth many yll workes. It maketh vs wery of ghoſtly lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. It putteth vs in fere of ghoſtly batayle / and dryueth vs frome the waye of penaunce. O fals ydelnes how many doeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> deceyue. Ydelneſſe is the ſnare that the deuyll hydeth ymonges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graſſe of the grene flouryſſhynge youthe / and ymonges the fallyngeleues leues of the vayne worldely Ioye and plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure / and very harde it is to ſcape it. Therfore beware that the deuyll in no wyſe fynde you in this ſnare / but yf ye be caught therin / breke out betymes before he catche holde vpon you. For whan he hathe holde vpon you / it is harde to breke awaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How we ſholde gyue vs to dyuers exercyſes.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:10104:6"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd bycauſe our mynde whiche is moche ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte vnto vanyte whyles we ben in this lyfe / abydeth neuer lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in one ſtate. Therfore we muſt dryue away ydelnes by dyuers chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of good exercyſes. As ſomtyme by good hande worke / &amp; conuenyent bodyly labour. Somtyme in prayer / ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme in ſtudy / or redynge of ſcrypture or of ſome good workes of holy doctours. Somtyme i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medytacyon and contemplacyon yf ye can attayne therto. And ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youre hande warke be other to the honour of god / to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profyte of poore people / orels for youre owne neceſſyte. And in euery thynge that ye ſhall do. Se fyrſt that it be lawfull for you to do it. Secu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darely yf it become you for to do it. Thyrdely whyder it be expedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for to do it. For all thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that ben lawfull and ſemynge for you to do / are not to be done / but yf they ben expedyent. Saynt Poule to wytnes. Omnia michilice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: ſet non omnia mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi expediunt. Therfore that thynge that is ſemy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge expedyent and not agayne the commaundement of god performe it / ſayenge before euery worke. In nomine pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tris. &amp;c. with a Pater noſter and un Aue maria.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of exercyſe in prayer and ſtudy.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Oure prayers beſydes the houres of dewty whiche muſt be preferred before ony thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / ye maye prolonge or make ſhort as the holy ghoſt gyueth grace of deuocyon or good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre. And beware that longe prayer gender not tedyouſneſſe. For better it is to praye often breuely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deuocyon / than longe vndeuoutly / excepte deuocyon be inſpired by longe deſyre. Beware alſo ye make no bande
<pb facs="tcp:10104:6"/> ne bone of nombre of pſalmes or prayers / but vſe them for the tyme that ye haue pleaſure and deuocyon in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And where deuocyon ſlacketh / than go to redynge or to ſome other exercyſe / ſo confortynge your ſpyrytes / auoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge the ſynne of ſlouth. In your ſtudy and redynge of bokes ſe that they ben conuenyent for you. And marke well all ſuche thynges as make to the exemple of good lyfe / bothe for to fele at your ſelfe / and to ſhewe it vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the ſame intent. And before ye go to rede or ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / ſaye thus. Spiritus ſancti gratia illuminet corda et corpora noſtra. With a Pater noſter. That is the grace of the holy ghoſt lyght on vs bothe ſoule and body. And after your redynge / remembre brefely what ye haue redde / and than ſay thus. Confirma hoc de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us quod operatus es in nobis. With a Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. How to be ordred at your vpryſynge / whan ye wake in the mornynge from ſlepe after the houre aſſygned to ryſe. Forthwith lyfte vp your harte to god / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytynge youre ſelfe to his proteccyon / and gyue hym tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes / for that he hathe preſerued you that nyght paſt / ſufferynge no vayne thoughtes to fall into your mynde / but ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſe you and fall vnto your prayer. Be neuer ouerco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with ſluggyſſhneſſe ne dulneſſe of body / as ſome be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that with gronynge and grutchynge ryſe oute of theyr beddes. But with a quycke mynde put awaye all ſlouth as though cryſt our ſpouſe dyd call you vnto maryage / ſayenge to youre ſelfe. Ryſe thou wretched body oute of of thy couche / make the redy and lyght thy lampe / go mete with thy ſpouſe / and do thy duty leeſt thou be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for comynge to late. Be not longe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apparyllynge of youre ſelfe / but apply you vnto your worke or ſeruyce
<pb facs="tcp:10104:7"/> enioyned to you for to do. With gladneſſe of mynde lette no vanytes appere in youre apparell / but kepe alwaye a ſemynge fourme and an vnyfourme waye in your dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge / vſynge nother to rude veſture ne to precious / but in a meane / no wyſe deſyrynge to pleaſe the worlde by it / but to honour god. Cal alſo beſeli vnto god for his helpe and grace / that ye maye be ſtronge agaynſt the malyce and power of your enemyes. For many haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in great peryl bothe of body and ſoule / bycauſe they haue not bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed them ſelfe &amp; honoured god at theyr vpryſynge. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſaye alwaye whan ye ryſe ſome bleſſynge and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er / as ye maye fynde in dyuers bokes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of herynge maſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it may be / here maſſe euery daye. For by that ye be made the more able to all good workes in the day folowynge / and proſper y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thynge. In maſſe tyme be dylygent aſmoche as ye maye to haue deuocyon / commyttynge youre ſelfe and all that longeth vnto you to hym that is there preſent. The maſſe is the veray memoryall of Cry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes paſſyon. Than yf ye wyl haue deuocyon / fall to ſome medytacyon of Cryſtes holy paſſyon. For there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge that kyndelyth mannes affeccyon ſo ſoone as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> medytacyon therof. Yf ye wyl be perfytely purged from vyces. Yf ye wyll be indued with vertues. Yf ye wyll be lyghtned with vnderſtandynge. Yf ye wyl haue vyctory of youre enemyes. Yf ye wyll haue conſolacyon in aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyte. Yf ye wyll haue ſweteneſſe with teres in your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Yf ye wyll departe pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly oute of this lyfe. Yf ye wyll haue redely euerlaſtynge ioye. Vſe deuoute medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon
<pb facs="tcp:10104:7"/> of cryſtes paſſyon in your maſſe herynge. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo euery other tyme before ye ſhall praye. The maſſe is of merueylous great effecte. For after the ſayenge of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynt Auſtyn. By euery maſſe deuoutly ſayd is there one ſoule delyuered out of purgatory / and one ſynner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Therfore here maſſe deuoutly / beſechynge our lorde ſaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. Bleſſed Iheſu let me ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhalbe ſtedfaſtly conuerted vnto the. And ſay this prayer. Ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a criſtiſanctifica me. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye be comonde / ſe that ye dyſpoſe your ſelfe before with hye deuocyon &amp; meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / by contrycyon / confeſſyon / and deuoute prayers / ſo that ye maye receyue your maker to the ſaluacyon and ſtrength of youre ſoules. And after to contynu the more ſtedfaſt in vertu.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How goddes ſeruyce and prayer ſholde be ſayde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeruyce that ye be commaunded for to ſay and al that longeth to obedyence / ſe that ye ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyll mooſt dylygently before all thynge. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prayers ben not acceptable to god / yf ye leue on thoſe thynges that ye are bounde to of dewte. Therfore whan the bell ryngeth to ſeruyce / conſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der as it were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trumpe that ſhalbe blowen at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Than hye you faſte to chyrche w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great mekeneſſe and fere / to treat and dyſcuſſe youre cauſes before god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt hye Iudge / mooſt myghty / mooſt ferefull / mooſt wyſe / mooſt tyghtwyſe / but yet mooſt mercyfull. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre that he is mercyful to all them that ben meke &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyent / and theyr complayntes and petycyons onely he delyteth to here. Therfore dyſpoſe your ſelf to mekenes afore your prayer / by ſome medytacyon / as of your ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:10104:8"/> lyfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſorynes therfore / of your fewe merytes &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable demerytes / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayly myſery in this lyfe / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infynyte peynes for ſynne after this lyfe. Of the great endeleſſe Ioye in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of the great goodnes of god / for delayenge our punyſſhement / for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſholde ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de our lyfe. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great mercy of our ſauyour Iheſu / ſufferynge bytter paſſyon for our redempcyon. Whiche al / but theſe pryncypally ben great cauſes for to meken our hartes / &amp; to ſerue god deuoutely. And whan ye haue great deuocy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on by mekeneſſe. Saye your ſeruyce &amp; prayers not onely in your one perſone / as for your ſelfe / but in the perſone of our moder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy chyrche. In y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche there be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome as pryſoners in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peynes of purgatory. Some as tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours that ben obſtynate ſynners. Some as ſuers for theyr pardon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben penytent. Some as mynyſters and ſeruauntes that ben in the ſtate of grace. Some ben aſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god / to be our patrones and vocates they ben ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly angels &amp; ſayntes. Now ymagyne that ſomtyme oure lorde ſpeketh vnto vs / &amp; we ſomtyme vnto hym in oure pſalmes and other ſeruyces that we ſaye. And ſomtyme we treat for the pryſoners. Somtye we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne of our aduerſaryes. Somtyme we deſyre hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpare his tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may haue ſpace to amende. Somtyme we labour to our patrones &amp; vocates for to helpe to opteyne fauour &amp; grace. Somtyme we magnyfy his power / his wyſdome / his goodneſſe / with lawe and prayſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thynke it no lytell cauſe that ye come to chyrche for. Before a temporall kynge cauſes ben dyſcuſſed / for this bodyly lyfe with great dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / fere / &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Moche more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought we w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great mekenes / reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; fere / dyſcus our ghoſtly maters for the ſafegarde and promo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of our ſoules before the hygh Iudge. And thoughe
<pb facs="tcp:10104:8"/> ye vnderſtande not what ye ſaye / conſyder that ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a poore wretche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath a complaynt or ſupplycacyon to put vnto the kynge / made by a lerned man / wherin all your deſyre is conteyned more expedyently / than ye can do it your ſelfe. Thus reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre where and in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and for what cauſe. And before ye go to your ſeruyce call for grace and ſaye. Rex chriſte cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime: tu corda noſtra poſſide: vt tibi laudes de bitas: reddamus omni te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore. Suffer not youre mynde to wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der as nere as ye maye. And ſaye after eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry houre where ye haue ben neclygent. Deus propiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us eſto michi peccatori. And whan ye haue ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is your duty / than ſaye your other prayers and memory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of ſayntes as your deuocyon is moeued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To haue a ſynguler deuocyon to ſome ſpecyall ſayntes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is very good to haue a ſynguler deuocyon / to ſome ſpecyall ſayntes / in whome ye haue great confydence to be youre aduocates / hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers / and defenders at all nedes to call on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whiche maye opteyne for you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben not worthy or able of your ſelfe. But mooſt ſpecyally in ony wyſe to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryous quene of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moder of cryſt at all tyme in mooſt louynge reuerence with mooſt hardy affeccyon louynge vnto her / as to moſte ſure refuge in all nedes / perylle / &amp; temptacyons / takynge her next cryſt / for mooſt hye and truſty vocate / gyuynge euery daye ſome ſynguler laude &amp; prayer to her mercyful goodnes. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your deuocyon and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to her made / be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more acceptable. Study to folowe her in pure chaſtyte &amp; clennes of body &amp; ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:10104:9"/> with all mekeneſſe of herte and lowlyneſſe to euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone in worde and dede. We haue ſo many enemyes and they ben ſo crafty / that without her helpe &amp; other holy ſayntes / we are not able to eſcape theyr daunger. The fore choſe you ſuche patrones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may helpe you in this dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous lyfe / and defende your ſoules from all cruell enemyes at the houre of dethe ſpecyally / and bry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge you gracyouſly to perpetuall ſafegarde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Te commendacyon of vyrgynyte.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emembre wyſely to whome ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſpouſed. Whome ye deſyre to haue in maryage / &amp; pray hym mekely that hathe inſpyred you with ſo good wyll / and gyuen you ſuche deſyre to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and perfourme the ſame. Ye haue promyſed youre vyrgynyte to Cryſt. Thynke this came not of your ſelfe For it is vnpoſſyble ſo to do and contynue / but onely by grace. Conſyder howe precyous a treſoure ye bere in a frayle veſſell. Remembre what rewarde / what glory / what crowne of Ioy ye ſhall haue / by kepynge of pure vyrgynyte. And fere what peyne / what ſhame / what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſyon / what da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n ye ſhall fall in yf it be loſt. What treaſure is better than that / wherwith ye maye by heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. wherin angelles greatly delyte. Wherby Cryſte hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe is allect and moeued to loue you ſpecyally. And to gyue (not onely hymſelfe) to you / but alſo euery thynge that is good. The ſwetenes of meke vyrgynyte gaue ſo ſwete an odour into heuen / that it made the kynge of all kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to haue ſuche a celeſtyall concupyſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mooſt meke vyrgyne Mary y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he deſcended frome heuen to erth for to be maryed vnto oure nature / but ye
<pb facs="tcp:10104:9"/> ſhall not be crowned tyll ye be well proued as golde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furneys. For ſcrypture ſayth / that he that is not te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted is not proued. Vyrgynyte is golde / your Cell is the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys / temptacyon is the fyre / the deuyll is the kyndler and blower of this fyre / your body is the erthen veſſell / wherin this golde is put to be proued. Whiche veſſell yf it be broken by ony vyolent fyre / the golde is ſhedde out and loſte / and the veſſell can neuer be repared and made hole agayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Vyrgynyte can not be get ne kepte without great labour and peyne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaſtyte &amp; vyrgynyte be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gyftes of a ſpyrytuall grace of god &amp; nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of our mery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. For we can not be chaſt or contynent / but yf god gyue it vs by grace. Therfore they ben vnworthy to haue ſo noble a gyfte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> refuſe to take ſome labour &amp; peyne for it. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thynke to be chaſt ymo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges delyces &amp; deynte cheryſſhynges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body / they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyl be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynent where great feeſtynge is &amp; deynte fare / they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fere not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ymo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges vnchaſt &amp; ryotous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones / &amp; not to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted for to be forced w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> etynge &amp; dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge &amp; not to be defiled / to hyde fyre in theyr boſome / &amp; not to be brent / they are ſore dyſceyued. For I thynke it very harde orels inpoſſyble. Therfore beware ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not dyſceyued preſumynge to moche in theſe thynges vpon your owne ſtrength. For w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trycyon &amp; afflyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the fleſſhe &amp; great helpe of gracce / true chaſtyte can nother be get nor kepte. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> glaſſe is frayle &amp; may endure no dyſtreſſe. Alſo great adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tures many ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes do curs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyce. Therfore beware ye ioperde not to ferre / but euermore eſchewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of yl. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:10104:10"/> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. Whoſoeuer loueth ꝑyl he ſhall peryſſhe therin</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of the vertue of ſadneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>E y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye be of ſadde behauyour / bothe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and outwarde geſture. Kepe your my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygently in ſadnes &amp; gyue it all to ſpyrytuall exercyſes / ſufferynge no vayne thoughtes to reſte therin. And myghtely ſubdew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſcence &amp; paſſyons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body / as wrath / carnall loue / bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely or worldly fere / ſenſuall ioye / or dyſolute laughynge For ye can not be well ordred outwarde / but yf theſe ben ordred &amp; well ruled inwarde / but yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outwarde beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour helpeth moche to ouercome theſe inwarde paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And therfore it behoueth to kepe wyſely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyly. v. wyttes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhal ſe / here / or touche / nothynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholde ſtyrre you to yll / or dyſteyne good maners / kepe youre ſyght cloſe towarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the eye is a theſe / &amp; wyll betraye the ſoule yf it be not warely kepte. Fyxe not your ſyght vpon beawtefull thynges and here no vayne ne vycyous comynge / ferynge leſt dethe wyll entre in at youre wyndowes &amp; infecte your ſoules with ſynne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of ſadneſſe &amp; dyſcrecyon in ſpeche &amp; other behauyoure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ooſt dylygently refrayne youre tonge &amp; ſpeke not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a reaſonable queſtyon be made vnto you / orels wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ben conſtrayned by euydent nede / &amp; than ſtudy to gyue an anſwere brefely &amp; mekely ſpekynge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſad cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce / reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; ſwete fere of god / exchewynge alway talky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſyons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / excepte it be of ghoſtly maters / &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ryght ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly perſones. Speke nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge but yf it be ſemynge for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10104:10"/> tyme / place / &amp; perſone. Myxte your honeſt myrth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / bothe in in ſpeche / laughy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / &amp; geſture of body / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rownynge or caſtynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght towarde ony perſone ſuſpectly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out lyſtynge or moeuynge of the heed or ony other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre vnſemyngely. Be gentyll w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out grutchy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. youre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce lowly &amp; cherefull w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out frownynge / lowrynge or deryſyon. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſpeke / lawgh / or ſmyle / ſe it be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſcornynge or lowde voyce. Be not to haſty nor to ſlowe in your goynge. Shewe no ſlouggyſſhneſſe in in your reſtynge. Inquyre not of other perſones co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacyons ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder theyr defautes. Refourme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is amys in other perſones w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony reprouynge. Nother prayſe ne dyſprayſe your ſelfe / nor greatly other ꝑſone. Speke nothynge to be reputed holy or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge. Gyue place to Ire betymes &amp; to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> multyply wordes agaynſt you / &amp; forgyue ſhortly theyr errour or neglygence. And thus ye ſhall kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertu of ſadneſſe / &amp; dyſcrecyon / whiche is is a great helpe to chaſtyte / &amp; to all other vertues. Wher to ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Poule dothe moeue vs / ſayenge. Let your ſadnes be knowen to all men. And ſo by good exemple ye maye profyte other &amp; meryte very moche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How refeccyon ought to be take.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>As a ſeke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receyueth his medycyne / ſo take your bodyly refeccyon. A ſeke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes his medycyne very bytter therfore he wyll take no more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſuffyſe for his helthe / &amp; yf he do / it may be to his hurte / ſo in lykewyſe conſyderynge the peryll vnto chaſtyte that is in meetes and drynkes / they ſholde be bytter vnto you / nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge gladde to take ony more thanne ſholde ſuſteyne nature / ferynge by to moche etynge and drynkynge for to gyue ſtrength vnto
<pb facs="tcp:10104:11"/> your aduerſary / and to nouryſſhe youre pryue enemy / increaſynge ſekenes of the ſoule. Therfore whan ye go vnto your meet / thynke alwaye vpon your chaſtye / fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge leſt the venym that is hydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in meet and drynke do not infecte the body with carnall luſte or ſlouth. And ſo conſequently the ſoule by concupyſcence &amp; neclygence in the ſeruyce of god. Saynt Ierom techeth holy vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynes wylleth that after they be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſed chyldehood and growynge aege they ſholde ete no fleſſhe / ne drynke no wyne / excepte the tyme of ſekeneſſe. And commaundeth that ſuche ſobreneſſe ſholde be kepte in meet and drynke that the body ſholde rather complayne / than to reioyce in full appetyte / ſo that the ſtomake ſholde not nede me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycynes / for to cauſe degeſtyon / but ſo to breke the appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyte of the body / that it be not leſſe apte vnto watchy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / prayer / ſtudy / or contemplacyon after the mele / than it was before. The wyſe man Salomon ſayth. I haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>termyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my ſelfe in mynde to reſtrayne my fleſſhe frome wyne. For this intent. That I myghte gyue my mynde vnto wyſedome and conynge / and eſchewe foly. Foly can not be auoyded / nor godly wyſedome opteyned but by abſtynence frome moche etynge and drynkynge. Therfore ſayth our ſauyoure Cryſt. Take hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youre hartes ben not accombered with Glotony. Exemple we haue of Danyell / Ananya / Mary / and Myſaell / chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of great abſtynence. To whome our lorde gaue excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wyſdome and connynge / ſo that they exceded ferre all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe lerned men in the kynkedome of Babylon. And all that euer haue had the grace of holy wyſdome of deuout contemplacyon / or reuelacyon hath come by it / by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of abſtynence. And conſtrary. Moche etynge &amp; dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge haue cauſed moche ſynne and foly. As it appereth
<pb facs="tcp:10104:11"/> of Noye and Loth with other / &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryche Glotone in the goſpell. Sewe not ſenſuall appetyte therfore to his full deſyre. So prouyde to your nede / that ye may ſwage hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / &amp; yet not ſatyſfy your bodyly appetyte. Regarde not the deyntyneſſe of meetes and drynkes / but nedely ſuſtentacyon of the frayle body contynually decayenge. And beware y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voluptuouſnes crepe not in vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloke of nede. Some there ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fere great abſtynence or wat chynge / bycauſe of ſekenes or wekenes of body / ferynge to be not ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to ſerue god. And I fere me many tymes it is but Excuſatio in peccatis. For full fewe ther be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue that feruour or loue to watche or to abſteyne ſo moche. And yf they had for the loue of god. I thynke he wolde gyue them dyſcrecyon withall / or otherwyſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde for them. I praye god it be not to moche / that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thynke to lytell. True dyſercco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n is to preferre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule before the body / whiche can not be without ſome peyne of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of behauynge at the borde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Yt honeſtly at your meet. Gyue place to youre better / bothe in order of ſyttynge and in fyrſte takynge of youre meet. Vſe no Ianglynge / tryflynge / nor lyghtnes at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borde / &amp; hate vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly detraccyon &amp; backbytynge. Be content with ſuche as is ſette before you without grutchynge / and fede not of to many dyſſhes nor to gredely. For in many meetes ſaythe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe man ye can not fayle of ſekeneſſe. And as ye fede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body with bodyly fode / ſo fede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ghoſtly fode / as by redynge of ſome holſome and ghoſtly werkes wherin your ſoules maye be edyfyed / gyue dylygence to
<pb facs="tcp:10104:12"/> the herynge therof with all ſylence / youre mynde and intent ſet holy therupon. And as ye ſe ſome great eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of theyr charytable goodnes wyll ſe ſome poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be ſerued afore them ſelfe. So in lyke wyſe ghoſtly / before euery mele ſerue thoſe poore ſoules in purgatory that haue leeſt helpe / with a pater noſter and an aue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ria / before ye ſerue your owne bodyes. And ye ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue (I thynke) ryght great mercy and rewarde of god therfore. Before ye ete ony mete / lyfte vp youre hartes deuoutely to god with laude and prayſe to hym and ſay grace / beſechynge hym to bleſſe your meet and you / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the refeccyon whiche ye ſhall take / maye be to ſtrengthe you in his ſeruyce / not fery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the body to rebell agaynſt the ſoule. After meet gyue thankes to god deuoutely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayenge grace / addy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte ende this lytell prayer. Deus det viuis gratiam: defunctis miſericor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diam: eccleſie ſue pacem: domino apoſtolico &amp; nobis peccatoribus vitam eternam. Amen. Wherto is graunted. lxv. yeres of pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How to be occupyed after meet / and to beware of temptacyon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter your dyner go to youre worke / ſtudy / or prayer as ye ben aſſygned to / and do that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygently / remembrynge alwaye god &amp; youre good angell preſent what ſoeuer ye do / &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply euery thynge that ye done reuete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to his honour. Beware of ydelneſſe and lyght maners / and forgete not your enemyes of the contrary behalfe / whiche neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth / but full beſyly laboureth contynually to deſtroye your ſoules w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ryght great crafte &amp; malyce. Haue them al
<pb facs="tcp:10104:12"/> waye ſuſpecte in euery thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhall do and thynke. And beware y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hyde hym not ymonge your good wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes by vayne glory / for thou he wyll make them nought Somtyme he wyll brynge in good thughtes &amp; purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for an yll intent / for to lette a better thynge / or for to inquyete the conſcyence. He cometh ſomtyme eaſely / ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme fereſely / ſomtyme pryuely / ſomtyme pertly. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ye flee fro hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorer he aſſayleth you. But what remedy? Truly we haue no ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth nor polycy in regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to our aduerſary. Therfore let vs not truſt in our ſelf Our lorde let hym be our ſtrengthe. Our good angelles and holy ſayntes helpe &amp; conforte to vs. Let vs therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte our ſelfe to hym / &amp; call for helpe betymes in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry temptacyon. Cleue ſtydfaſtly to his loue / with fere of his dyſpleaſure. Remembrynge what peyne he ſuffered to brynge man into the ſtate of grace. And therfore ſuffer not to be brought oue therof for a lytell ſhort pleaſure or for ſuffery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge a lytell dyſpleaſure or a ſhort peyne. It ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth god very moche / whan ony perſone auoydeth temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyon betymes / and falleth to prayer and prayſynge of god. For than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuyll had forged for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes great hurte / it tourned vpon his owne heed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo reſyſteth / ſhall haue double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / bothe for his vyctory &amp; for his prayer vnto god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How to ouercome temptacyon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F he be very ferce agaynſt you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyon or trybulaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / how ſoeuer greuous it be / dyſpere not. Thynke there ben. xii. dyuers houres in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye / they ſhall not be alyke vnto you. Some good and ſome badde. Thynke how oure lorde loketh vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on you to proue youre ſtydfaſtneſſe &amp; manlyneſſe / for to
<pb facs="tcp:10104:13"/> gyye you the larger crowne of glory / and ſaye with To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be. Yf we haue not taken good thynges of the hande of god / why ſholde we not take yll. And remembre holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yntes that haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> troubled ſo before. And marke it wel that whome ſoeuer god wyll vyſyte with grace and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolacyons / hym wyll he fyrſte proue in the fyre of trybu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyon. Therfore neuer gyue vp to youre aduerſary / ne grutche not with the troubleous temptacyons / nor loke tomoche of that that is layde to you by temptacyon / but go forwarde aboute youre good beſyneſſe / as thoughe ye dyſdeyned to here of ſuche thynges. Or els ſpeke thus in your mynde / refourmynge your ſoule. Lo my ſoule / lo how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll knocketh at thy gate. Yf thou ſuffereſt hym to come in / god thy ſtrength ſhall go from the / and thou ſhalt peryſſhe with great myſery and ſuffer great peyne and ſhame before god and man. O thou frayle bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy / all this wyckedneſſe procedeth of the. Beware thou be not ſubiecte vnto the deuyll. Conſyder how that god is preſent / to ſe how thou ſhalt fyght with thyne enemy Cry for helpe vnto heuen / that they maye aſſyſte vs and put awaye our aduerſaryes. Thou can not ſe them / and therfore the batayll is the more peryllous. Suffer and take vpon the a lytell peyne / and thynke how pleaſaunt thy vyctory ſhalbe. And contrary yf thou folowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhort pleaſure of thy temptacyon / eternall peyne wyll folowe. Therfore beware / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fall to prayer / &amp; what ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll ſpeketh in you by te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyon / thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke it is not your worde nor youre doynge / therfore care not for it / but go forwarde / truſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that as after great ſtormes / cometh fayre weder. Soo after great trybulacyon ſhall folowe ghoſtly conſolacyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10104:13"/>
               <head>¶ How ſtudy or medytacyon in holy wrytynge profyteth moche agaynſt temptacyon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or this cauſe I wolde ye ſholde alwaye fere truſtynge nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vpon your owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth but alwaye ſuſpecte your owne fraylte / and as a donne that fereth the hawke dothe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munely vſe the ryuer ſyde / and as i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a glaſſe doth ſpy in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadowe of the hawke flyenge for to deuoure her / and ſo is aware of her &amp; ſaueth her ſelfe. So I wolde ye ſholde do. The ryuers or waters ben the ſentences of holy ſcrypture / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of our ſauyour Iheſu cryſt / &amp; of other holy ſayntes. Whiche flowynge fro the mooſt clere fountayne of the dyuyne wyſedome dothe ſhewe &amp; dyſcouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubtyll crafte &amp; fals ſuggeſtyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our enemy the deuyll / &amp; techeth vs how we ſhalbe ware of hym / for to eſcape his daunger. Nothynge ſwageth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyſcence more / nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge putteth yll thoughtes awaye better / than with the ſtudy or medytacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god &amp; holy redynge. Vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche I wolde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſholde ſo accuſtome your my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and occupy your hartes ſo ther upon / that whan ye go to bedde ye myght fall on ſlepe in the thynkynge of ſome ſentence of holy ſcryptures or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yntes lyues &amp; dreame of them in your ſlepe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſſoone as ye ſhall wake / they maye cleue to youre memory. And therfore whan ye be troubled or waked by the crafte or ylluſyon of youre enemy / beware of vayne thoughtes be tymes / auoydynge all dulneſſe of body and mynde. And occupy you thus orels in prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of mekeneſſe.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:10104:14"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake this for a ſure concluſyon / though chaſtyte be the very floure and beaute of all vertues / yet without the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of mekeneſſe it can not growe / but it fadeth and vanyſſheth away / as ſhowe agaynſt the ſonne. Mekenes is the fundacyon of all vertues / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrengthe of the ſoule / the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſyon of our great enemy the deuyll / a veſſell of all grace / the moder of peas / the reſtynge place of the holy ghoſt. And pryde contrary wyſe is begynnynge of all ſynne &amp; mooſt weke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the ſoule / whiche expelled angell frome heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and man from paradyſe. Yf ye ioye in ony thynge / ioye in our lorde / &amp; not for that ye come of noble vertuous lyguage or of ryche parentes / nor for that ye preferre pouerte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ryches / nor for that ye haue forſaken ryche marya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / but ſhewe by mekenes how nere you ben our meke ſpouſe Cryſte / the more meke / the more nere hym ye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beware that ye ben not proude of mekenes / but dyſpyſe your ſelfe / dyſpyſe none other perſone. And ſet noughte to be dyſpyſed / but rather be glad. Yf ye wyll be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpouſe of Cryſte / whiche beynge mooſt ryche in heuen / choſe to be mooſt poore in erthe. He choſe a poore moder / a poore houſe to be borne in / where he was mooſt honoured in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He came hyder to take dyſpytes / reproues / &amp; great peynes mekely as a lambe. Therfore folowe this lambe as ye haue knowen other vyrgynes do before where ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ye go. And thynke that ye can neuer be to meke / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderynge what grace cometh alwaye therby.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of obedyence.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ye haue true mekeneſſe / ye ſhall repute euery perſone your better / &amp; youre ſelfe as a ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te
<pb facs="tcp:10104:14"/> or a hande mayde / whatſoeuer degre ye be of. Wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on folowe perfyte obedyence / whiche vneth god to man / &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to god in perfyte charyte. Saynt Barnarde ſayth Yf ye wyll be wyſe / be obedyent. For thus it is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yf thou coueyteſt wyſedome / obſerue and do that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the / and god ſhall gyue it the. This obedyence muſt be obſerued (not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruyle fere) but with good affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of loue &amp; charyte (not for fere of peyne) but for loue of Iuſtyce. Obedyence is that vertue that graffeth all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule. It preſecueth and kepeth them ſurely after they ben graffed. It is better than ſacryfyce For by ſacryfyce is gyuen away the temporall goodes / and by obedyence is vtterly lefte and forſaken the owne ſelfe wyll. Of our owne wyll cometh all ſynne. Than yf we forſake our owne wyll / reſygnynge it to god and to our ſuperyoure / we forſake all ſynne / for we may do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge but as they wyll. Yf they wyll no ſynne / we ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore beynge obedyent / maye do no ſynne. What is than more expedyent tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue obedyence (whiche hadde) we nede to fere no peynes of hell. The order of obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is thus. It is more our duty to obey god than man / the ſuperyour than the inferyour / better to obey your owne heed than a ſtraunger. And it is ſpecyally good to obey one to another / yf it letteth not the obedyence to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryour. A true obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer is gladde to be ſeruyſeable vn to euery one of his company / &amp; ſory to be chargeable or comberous to them. Louynge &amp; gentyll to all / &amp; deuoute vnto god. The greater that perſone be that is dyſobeyed the greuoſer is the inobedyence. The more eaſy the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement be / the more greuoſer is the contempte. And yf it fortune you to contempne the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement (as god forbydde) of youre heed / beware in ony wyſe ye
<pb facs="tcp:10104:15"/> contempne not the remedy / whiche is meke penaunce / redy to be ſory with ſubmyttynge of your ſelf to correccy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / fallynge to the fete of them whome ye offende. Note well this ſayenge of ſaynt Barnarde. Whan my ſupery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our (ſythen he) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth me to ſcyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / yf a worde per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunce eſcape thrughe neclygence or forgetynge my ſelfe. I knowlege my ſelfe gylte of inobedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce venyally / but yf wyttyngly &amp; with delyberacyon of a contempte / I breke out into wordes / wylfully brekynge the lawe of ſylence. I dyſcerne and Iudge my ſelfe a greuous ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / &amp; that deedly and dampnably / yf I perceyuer inpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytent vnto my lyues ende. For Cryſte ſayth to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rulers. Who that dyſpyſeth you / dyſpyſeth me. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore kepe wel this vertue of obedyence vnto god / &amp; your ſuperyour / and god ſhalbe obedyent vnto your prayers and petycyons. And be alwaye redy to obey with a good wyll without ony taryenge or delay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may ſaye this verſe truely. Paratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cor meuz deus: paratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. My harte is redy good lorde / my harte is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to obey in wyll and dede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of this vertue of pacyence.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han ye ben troubled with iniuryes / repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders / with enuye / or malyce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt you / with loſſe of goodes / or aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte and ſekeneſſe. Remembre your ſelfe be tymes / before ony paſſyon of heuyneſſe or inpacyence ryſeth in you / thynkynge they be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of your ſpouſe Iheſu Cryſte ſende for your welthe / other to refourme your maners / or to proue your loue / whyder it be ſtedfaſt and faythfull or not. And not onely
<pb facs="tcp:10104:15"/> ſuffer them pacyently / but alſo gladly / as ſaynt Poule dyd and many other holy men and women before / &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder it is but foly and vayne to loke for heuen with plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure and delytes / ſeynge that Cryſte our ſouerayne lorde and ſpouſe aſcended not to heuen / but by manly fyght / with great peyne &amp; paſſyon. And that it were no ryghte nor ſemynge / that the ſeruaunt ſholde ſtande in better condycyon tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mayſter. Better it is to take pacyent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / that thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye can not auoyde with hope of a good rewarde / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to grutche w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuerte of great punyſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t And byleue it truely that your aduerſary can not do you ſo moche good / by no fauour / ſeruyce or benefyte / as he dothe whan he troubleth you / yf ye take it pacyently / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out grutche or malyce agaynſt hym. And thanke god therof / as for a token of great loue. Ye wyll aſke me who can do thus. I anſwere? Euery perſone that is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of grace / and wyll apply hym ſelfe therto dylygently / as I ſuppoſe truly. Cryſte ſuffered dethe for vs / leuynge to vs exemple (not onely hym ſelfe) but alſo many holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yntes / that by theyr exemple we ſholde folowe theyr ſtep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes. Exemple we haue of ſaynt Katheryne of Seene be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge a chylde. Whan her fader and moder / bredren &amp; ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtren were ſette all to do her dyſpleaſure / &amp; to trouble her holy mynde / from her ghoſtly purpoſe / ſhe ordred &amp; dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in her deuoute ymagynacyon / to accepte her fader as Cryſte / her moder as our lady / her dredren &amp; ſyſtren as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles. And whatſoeuer was ſayde or done to her by them / ſhe toke it as it had ben done of Cryſte / of his moder / or of his apoſtles / With meke pacyence / gladde obedyence / and louely obſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / thrughe the whiche / ſhe deſerued increace of moche grace. Our lorde alſo byd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth vs to do good to them that hate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs / and promyſeth
<pb facs="tcp:10104:16"/> vs the kyngedome of heuen therfore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The concluſyon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the daye is almooſt paſte / wherin ye haue taſted bothe ſwete and ſoure / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye / ye haue had ſomtyme trybulacyon &amp; ſomtyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacyon / bothe ſpyrytually &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porally. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tourne vnto your ſelfe / cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge to remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dylygent ſerche / how ye haue expended y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> daye in euery thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue done or lefte vndone / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> behoued you to haue do / or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> became you not to do / beynge ſory for euery defaute / &amp; bewayle all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is yll. For thoughe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morny<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ye purpoſed for to forſake all yll / and for to exercyſe good werkes / yet often tymes whan ye reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre your ſelfe well / ye ſhall fynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue done many ylles / and fewe good thynges. Therfore in ſuche cauſes ordeyne and kepe a chapytre euery day for your ſelfe. Be rygoryous vpon youre owne defautes / &amp; let nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſcape vncorrecte / yf ye wyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſhall ſpare you. Examyne how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon hath be obedyent vnto the feythe / &amp; how ſhe hathe occupyed her all day. Alſo how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl hath be ruled by reaſon / &amp; kepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rules of goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes / &amp; whether ſhe hath be to famylyer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſenſualyte. How y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herynge / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpeche / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery cenſe &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body hath be occupyed euery houre of the day / &amp; in what place. The ymagynacyon &amp; memory w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whome they haue ben occupyed. Se whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the body haue be remyſſe and ſlowe in ſeruyce / wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge / ſtudy / or labour. Serche yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthe haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ony vayne / ſturdy / or vnclenly wordes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende other god or man. Or yf ye can fynde ony other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb facs="tcp:10104:16"/> agaynſt good cryſten maners. Than bowe downe your harte &amp; body mekely / &amp; praye god of forgyueneſſe / ſubmyttynge your ſelfe to his correccyon / &amp; be gladde to take it in this lyfe / &amp; to do wylfull penaunce. There ben iij. exercyſes of ghoſtly helthe / whiche ben neceſſary for euer perſone to vſe dayly. The. i. is to knowe youre ſelfe a ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner / &amp; to be ſory for your ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. The. ij. is to purpoſe for to be ware of ſynne / &amp; to forſake it for euermore. The iij. is for to inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to be confeſſed of all your ſynnes / and do penaunce for the ſame. who ſoeuet before theyr ſlepe dothe theſe. iij. thynges / ſurely though it behapped (as god forbyd) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde dye ſodeynly / yet there is hope of grace &amp; ſaluacyon / thoughe he were in deedly ſynne. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ye haue made thus recollacyon of your ſelfe / &amp; gade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your defautes togyder / bynde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dell &amp; caſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre of hell / that is remembrynge the peynes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for them / beynge ſory and in full purpoſe neuer to fall agayne. And be more ſory for the offence of god / than for the dammage that ſholde folowe therof to youre ſelfe. Than after your prayers ſayd / dreſſe you towarde your bedde with mooſt honeſt maner / as thoughe Cryſt your ſpouſe were preſent. And whan ye be ſet in youre bedde / bleſſe you with the ſygne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myttynge your body and ſoule vnto youre ſpouſe Cryſte and to the kepynge of youre good angell. Than laye you downe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly with your armes a croſſe vpon youre breeſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware than dylygently of vayne thoughtes / and putte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye vayne temptacyons quyckly. Remembre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youre enemy the deuyll ſlepeth not / and how that god dothe ſe all your behauyour / bothe in mynde and without forth. Therfore vſe clenly maner w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſelfe. And beware of carnall deſyres. Tender not youre body tomoche w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſofte
<pb facs="tcp:10104:17"/> &amp; warme lyenge. Satyſfy not youre body in al that it de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyreth (yf ye do) it ſhall put you in great ieopardy. Yf ye can not ſlepe ſhortly after ye ben layde / occupy your ſelfe in pſalmes / orels vpon your beedes / and with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dryue all fantyſyes frome your mynde / excepte it be occupyed aboute holy thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / by good medytacyon. So fallynge on ſlepe as I haue ſayde before. Thus after the nyghte be ronne vnto matyns tyme / than ryſe cherely / and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to occupy the daye agayne / after the counſeyll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And as youre rule dothe teche you and bynde you / that ye may lyue here ſoberly / mekely / &amp; iuſtly in clennes of conſcyence / &amp; hereafter obteyne eternall lyfe / &amp; ioye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende / whiche our lorde Iheſu graunt vs. Amen.</p>
               <closer>DEO GRATIAS.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Impry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by me wynkyn de worde. The yere of our lorde. M. CCCCC. &amp; xx. Of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. xx. daye.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde, a tripartate device with a mark and initials of William Caxton in the central part. The sun over a crescent moon with stars in the upper portion, and a centaur shooting a bow and arrow toward a dog below (McKerrow 23)</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>Wynkyn .de. Worde.</q>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10104:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
